Intel(R) BootIMG.FLB file format change
======================================
October 23, 2020

Contents
========
- OVERVIEW
- CUSTOMER SUPPORT
- LEGAL


Overview
========
The BootIMG.FLB file format has changed to allow using four part Device IDs
when necessary to distinguish the correct NVM image for a device. All utilities
and software are able to read older versions of BootIMG.FLB. However, you must
update any utilities software you use to a more recent version to use the new
BootIMG.FLB. Please upgrade to the following versions (or a more recent
version):

- BootUtil, v. 1.3.5.xxx
- Intel(R) Proset for Windows* Device Manager, v. 17.1.xxx
- SMASH, v2-2.0.0.58

The current version can be downloaded at Intel's Network Products information
website: http://www.intel.com/network


CUSTOMER SUPPORT
================
- Main Intel web support site: http://support.intel.com

- Network products information: http://www.intel.com/network

Intel Wired Networking project hosted by Sourceforge:
http://sourceforge.net/projects/e1000


LEGAL / DISCLAIMERS
===================
Copyright (C) 2012 - 2020, Intel Corporation. All rights reserved.

This software and the related documents are Intel copyrighted materials, and
your use of them is governed by the express license under which they were
provided to you ("License"). Unless the License provides otherwise, you may not
use, modify, copy, publish, distribute, disclose or transmit this software or
the related documents without Intel's prior written permission.

This software and the related documents are provided as is, with no express or
implied warranties, other than those that are expressly stated in the License.

Intel technologies may require enabled hardware, software or service activation.

No product or component can be absolutely secure.

Your costs and results may vary.

Intel, the Intel logo, and other Intel marks are trademarks of Intel
Corporation or its subsidiaries.

*Other names and brands may be claimed as the property of others.


